Today, as you can
see, I am at the Royal Palace of Madrid,
because I wanted to talk a little about the
architecture of this building and its
history, because I find it very
interesting.
And I would like to start by talking a little about the
place where we are.  Here,
as you can see, we have on this side the
Almudena Cathedral, which
we will talk about a little
later.  And we have the Royal Palace.  And
what I find important about
this place
is its location, because before
this royal palace existed, there was the
Royal Alcázar of Madrid, the residence of
the Kings of that time, which was a
building that had been quite transformed.
Originally it was a fortress, it was
like a medieval Islamic castle, a
castle of the Muslims from the
time of the Moors, when they were in
Spain during the Middle Ages.  And it was that
fortress that was conquered by the
Christians.  But even so, Madrid
remained a village,
a small, unimportant town, didn't it?   It
was quite insignificant
compared to historical capitals
like Toledo, Burgos, León, and so on.
And there wasn't just one capital of Spain
at that time, but rather it was
called the itinerant court, because the king
and the court spent their time traveling from
city to city according to
political needs, according to the war, according to the
needs of the king in general.
So, well
, all that until the year
when King Philip Segi
decided to change, well, to establish
Madrid as the seat of the Court, he
called it the Unique Court.  So, Madrid
became the seat of government
of Spain, partly with the
purpose of unifying the kingdoms of
Spain, the kingdoms of the peninsula and
establishing a single seat.
He settled in the Royal
Alcázar that stood on this site, in honor of Philip II.  That
Royal Alcázar had a
rather medieval architecture with towers, uh a
stone architecture
and that he, Felipe Segi and some of
his successors were uh reforming it,
were remodeling it, were changing
the appearance of that building
and as a result it gave uh what
we have today as the Royal Alcázar of
Madrid, which was a hybrid between
medieval and Renaissance with a facade
with columns, a portal in the center,
two side towers with spires.  It is
a rather sober architecture,
characteristic of the Habsburgs and of
Madrid.  The Habsburgs were the House of Austria
, the
kings who ruled Spain at that
time.  This architecture was
characterized by being made
entirely of brick, but with
stone details.  It had spires on
the towers and it is an architecture that can
still be seen today in the center
of Madrid, in some churches, in the
Plaza Mayor, for example, this
architecture very characteristic of the
Habsburgs.
When in the year 1700 the king, the
last king of the Habsburgs, Charles
II, died, he died without leaving a single
heir.  So what happened was that there was
a war of succession where in the
end the Bourbons, who ruled in Versailles, took power and the throne of
Spain
.  It was the family
of Louis XIV, the Sun King of France.
And well, the nephew of
Charles II, the last king of the
Habsburgs, was Philip of Anju, who was
Philip of Bourbon, who lived his
childhood in Versailles.  And when he took the
throne of Spain, he wanted something more
monumental.  The Bourbon style of governance is quite noticeable and is
reflected in the architecture
.
In comparison with the Habsburgs,
when Philip II
took power in Spain, he was
still residing in
the Royal Alcázar of Madrid, but in
1734 this Royal Alcázar
burned down.  The Royal Alcázar
had a great deal of
art, a great deal of sculpture, of
painting, much of which was lost in
that fire,
but much was also saved.  And the
most important work that was saved is
Velázquez's Las Meninas, which
are painted inside the Alcázar.  In
other words, if you look at the room where
the Meninas are, well, it's a
room that was inside the
Alcázar, it's no longer preserved, so we don't
know exactly what the
internal layout was like, but it's very
interesting to see it from that point of
view.  Well, these works of art that were saved
were saved because they
started throwing them from the windows of the
Alcázar
and into the street, and well,
the meninas were saved, among some other
paintings.
Well, when this building burned down,
King Philip V wanted to
rebuild the palace, but in a
style a little more to what he was
used to, in the more exuberant Baroque style
of Italy and France, in keeping with
the European palaces that were being
built at that time.
Then he hired the Italian architect
Filipo Yubarra,
who designed a huge palace with
many courtyards, with a huge extension
that in the end they realized
that the project was not viable because it was
too big, too expensive and
also the architect died before it
could be built.  Then,
Giovanni Batista Squetti,
Yubarra's successor architect, designed this palace
that we see right here.
And something I love about this palace, and
that I find very interesting, is the
rhythm of its architecture.  It's
a bit like the design that that one has, and that
design is very similar.  but
identical,
quite inspired by the design of the
Lufre palace, made by Bernini.
In Paris, the Louvre Museum,
the Louvre Palace, was remodeled
by Louis XIV
and
its architecture was entrusted to several
architects, among them Jean Lorenzo
Bernini, the famous architect of the
Italian Baroque, the most
important of the Italian Baroque architects
and of Baroque sculpture
as well, he was perhaps in my opinion
Bernini is the sculptor, the best
sculptor in history.  There he is up there
with Michelangelo.  Uh,
and well, he was also a great architect,
and if you look at the plans that Bernini made
for the project of the
Lufre palace, he made three projects.  The
first one had a kind of roundabout which
for me is the best of the three, but
the king didn't like it.  Then he made another
project with a kind of exedra
set back into the palace, which
the king also disliked.  And then he did a
third project that is almost exactly the
same as this one.  I'm going to show you some
plans so you can see the similarity.
And this third project by Bernini,
like this one, has a base of
rustication,
a giant order in the columns, in
the upper floors, and is topped
by a cornice with a balustrade at
the top.  It has a
central section with columns and the
sides with pilasters.
It is an architecture that is entirely made of
stone, it is entirely in the
Italian style.  You no longer see those
spires, those towers with spires
from the Habsburgs, you no longer see so much of
that brick architecture with
stone details.  Now it is
entirely a stone building.
Now the interior of this palace has
a central courtyard.  That central courtyard
is also very similar to the plans.  by
Bernini for his palace in Lufre.  It is very
similar because it has
two floors of arcades, two levels of
arcades, and the top floor is
recessed to give a slightly
brighter feeling, to give more
light to the interior of the courtyard and the interior
of the palace, and also to give a
slightly more human sense of scale to the
interior, to the center of the palace.
However, it is
exactly the same, very similar.  It seems
that the architect really knew
Bernini's project for the
Luf Palace well.  And the drawings are very
similar, Bernini's drawings, to the
result, what came out here in
the Royal Palace.
Oh, another really interesting thing
is the interior of the halls, isn't it?  The
architect Giovanni Batista Squetti was
mainly in charge of the
architecture, uh, a little bit how
the spaces were distributed, uh the
details of the exterior, the style, but
the interior rooms were
decorated by different artists and
architects.
Oh, and the interior of this palace... the
exterior looks very baroque, doesn't it?  Very
Italian Baroque, quite defined,
but the interior is very particular
because there is a certain balance between
Baroque and a very exuberant Baroque and Neoclassical style
, right?  There is gold
everywhere, there is a lot of rococo decoration,
and it has two rooms in particular
that have a lot of rococo detail
inside the palace, which is the
throne room.
And there's another room that's completely
rococo with many frivolous details,
and
well, there's architecture
or rather details like Chinese, which is what
was fashionable at that time.
There is a living room in the style of Pompeii and
Herculaneum, like those
Roman houses of antiquity that had just been
discovered at that time and were
fashionable.
In short, inside the palace
there is enormous eclecticism, there is a great
variety of styles
and that chapel it has, which although it is
quite baroque, well it has baroque with
many neoclassical details, but very
exuberant, very exuberant.   This
is the interior of this palace, just
as the king liked it, the kings
who built this building,
because King Philip V who commissioned
the work at the beginning, but later his
successors,
especially Charles III, were the ones who
completed it and
who put the most of his touch inside the
palace.  It must be remembered that this
Bourbon dynasty,
eh, they are no longer like the Habsburgs, they
are no longer austere, they are no longer French, and
the French of the family of Louis
XIV like monumentality,
exuberance.  If you see those French palaces
like Versailles, well, you see a
much greater exuberance.  And this is
a reflection of all of
this.  You see it in architecture.
eh, the one about the change of dynasty.
From the time the Habsburgs ended and
the Bourbons began to rule, you see in
the architecture this change towards
more French influences,
more Italian influences, and even at the
urban level in the city they began to
plan more in the
Baroque style, right?  More axial than
more integral with the city, they make the
Paseo del Prado.  If you look at
the city of the Habsburgs, it is
completely an organic layout, it is
completely
a medieval layout, well the Bourbons
begin to change this as soon as they ascend
to the throne.
And on the other side,
over here, we have
the Almodena Cathedral, which many
people think is a very
old cathedral, but in reality it is a
20th century cathedral.   It is not
as old a cathedral
as it seems.  The thing is, it has a
rather neoclassical style on the
outside, but inside it is a
rather eclectic result of
architectural ambitions.  Hm.  From the
beginning of the 20th century and the end of the
19th century.  This cathedral began to be
built in 1893,
if I'm not mistaken, 90-something, and was
completed in 1993, that is, it took
approximately 100 years to
build, but in the 20th century
modern architecture began to become fashionable and popular.
So, there were several changes both
in the architecture and in the
people who built this cathedral.
If you look at the crypt, which is the
most important space in this
Almudena Cathedral, it's made in a neo-
Romanesque style and I think it's
masterful how it's developed, but
if you look at this facade
specifically and how
the stone is carved, how it's
designed, the truth is that it's
quite noticeable.  as in the 20th century it
lost much of that
artistic mastery that the stonemasons and
sculptors had.  If you look, for
example, at the capitals
of the columns, the
truth is that they don't have very good
details, I mean, it's not the
same when you compare it to
those masterful capitals that the
royal palace has. It's as if they
tried to make it a bit in the
same style, with the same
materials, on the outside, but that
artistic and sculptural skill that they had in
antiquity, well, before
modernity, the artists, well,
I think that was quite lost.  It's a
very nice building, it's
very well made, but it's not the
same.  And inside you can also
see that lack of, well, that lack
of art and technique more than anything else.   Well, that's
all for today.
I hope you enjoyed it, I hope you
learned a little about the Royal Palace,
and well, we'll see each other very soon to
talk about other architectural spaces
in Madrid.